Under those circumstances,
why do we need to militarily intervene
down there?
It's not because we can't. Can we
overpower Venezuela militarily?
Obviously.
That's not that challenging.
That's not to say that after you've done
this so that you're sitting on a gold
mine. On the contrary, the big problem
is you go into a place like that,
there's the risk that you make yourself
[music] responsible for everything that
happens down there. You ultimately turn
it into a bottomless pit for money
[music] and resources from the United
States at a point in time when I don't
think we could afford that or or
necessarily need to do it.
Uh and then what kind of response do you
get out of Latin America?
Uh we're not widely loved in what Latin
America, never have been.
Some of that is justified, some of it
isn't, it doesn't matter.
But if you go into Venezuela, do you
turn this whole episode into a rallying
point for every Latin American country,
>> [music]
>> every contented revolutionary?
Hi, I'm John Kiriakou and welcome back
to Deep Focus. Here on the show, we like
to talk about the big issues in the
news, whether it's the Russia-Ukraine
war or what's happening in Afghanistan
Afghanistan or or soon what may happen
in Venezuela.
Uh but there are other issues that are
just as important such as the the sorry
state of American politics.
Well, sometimes there are people who are
who are experts in one area
who are unacknowledged experts in other
areas. That's our guest today. Before we
get to him though, I want to ask you to
please do me a solid. And if you enjoy
this content, please like, share, and
most importantly, subscribe. It helps us
a lot with the YouTube algorithm.
Well, I am proud to call Colonel Doug
McGregor a friend.
Doug is a retired colonel in the US
Army. He's a former senior government
official. And when I say senior, I mean
senior most government official.
President Trump at the end of his first
term named Colonel McGregor US
Ambassador to Germany.
There were a lot of senators who didn't
like that because Doug speaks his mind,
which is one of the reasons why we're
friends. Uh and so he went over to the
Pentagon as one of the highest ranking
officials in that department. He's also
an acclaimed author, a consultant, and a
political commentator.
An armor branch officer by background,
Doug was a leader in an early tank
battle in the Gulf War. I remember it
very well, as a matter of fact. He was
also a top planner in the 1999 NATO
bombing of Yugoslavia. His 1997 book
Breaking the Phalanx argued for radical
reforms inside the United States Army,
and that is what keeps him as relevant
as he is today.
Colonel Doug McGregor, thanks for
joining us. Good to see you again.
Well, John, it's good to see you as
well. You're looking You're looking
great.
>> Thank you, sir. And as are you.
Well, we're trying to stay alive.
>> Yeah, we are. We're trying to stay
alive. Especially within range of
Washington, D.C., right?
>> Which is easier said than done.
>> [laughter]
>> I have so many questions for you.
I almost don't know where to begin. But
just 5 or 10 minutes before we started
recording, 5 or 10 minutes ago, I
received a breaking news update uh from
Associated Press. And I wanted to get
your preliminary thoughts on this. The
The White House has just announced that
the US will send an aircraft carrier
battle group
to Venezuela.
Hm. What do you think we should make of
this? On the one hand, it's clear that
Donald Trump hates Nicolas Maduro. Uh he
wants that government gone. He wants to
be able to return Venezuelan um
undocumented
uh immigrants to Venezuela without
having the left arguing that he's
sending them to certain, you know, death
or prison terms or whatever.
But do you think that this that this
president, who really was elected on an
anti-war platform,
will go to a war of choice? It certainly
looks that way. Hm. I mean, ideally, if
we're going to send an aircraft carrier
battle group, I'd prefer that they
pulled into port and enjoyed some
liberty down in Venezuela. My limited
experience with Venezuelans is that
they're Yeah, they're lots of very nice
people.
The women are very attractive, the food
is good, the weather is nice, but I
guess that's not going to happen.
But that would be my preference. No, I'm
afraid you're right. We You know, this
business with Venezuela has been going
on for a long time. You've got to go You
know, you know that from your own
experience in the agency.
There have been multiple attempts to
manipulate, influence politics down
there.
>> [clears throat]
>> Why the president in particular at this
point in time is so interested in
involving himself down there is a bit of
a mystery.
But we know certain things from from
history. We know, obviously, that
you know, the Venezuelans,
uh the Mexicans, the Cubans, all three
of those countries strongly backed the
communist cause during the Spanish Civil
War.
Now, I Some of that was undoubtedly
ideological. It also has to do with a
sort of revolutionary past down in that
part of the world, particularly with
Bolivar, the you know, the uh
uh Yeah, Bolivar. Simon Bolivar, yeah.
Yeah,
and the revolution that they had.
Fact, there's a McGregor who was
involved in that, but we won't talk
about [laughter] that right now.
He was another rogue mercenary or
something that decided to get out there
and muck around. Anyhow,
uh
the the point is that some things never
change, and attitudes in those three
states are very similar to what they
were years ago.
That doesn't necessarily mean you have
to go to war with them.
Then there's this issue of drugs, which
is very odd, because Venezuela is not a
drug hub. Do some illicit drugs
pass through the country? Sure. They
pass through lots of countries. And by
the way, contrary to what President
Trump is saying, they're still finding
their way into the United States.
But that's not a point of origin for
massive drug production. It certainly
isn't a point of origin for fentanyl,
which tends to come up from Mexico,
the Mexican cartels, obviously. And
Mexico is, for all intents and purposes,
an organized crime state.
I'm not sure why we are so interested
going this far afield to Venezuela when
we've got a much bigger problem right on
our border.
Uh the other thing is that the CIA has
been involved down there, as you know.
And in 2019, there was a concerted
attempt to try and stage a coup and
remove the government.
Now,
we always have to mention that Venezuela
is probably or or could be, we don't
really know, we think, is the largest
oil has the largest oil reserves of any
country in the world. Okay.
They're very deep, these reserves, by
the way.
And it just so happens that we have the
best deep drilling capability of any
country in the world.
>> I mean, our our oil engineers in general
are the best.
Now, why do we have to go to war
to get to the oil reserves? That's a
mystery to me. Even President Trump has
stated flatly that Mr. Maduro came to
him and made an offer that would have
given us a stake in the oil and gas
reserves.
In fact, he characterized Mr. Maduro's
offer as essentially everything.
And in fact, that was relatively recent.
That was just in the last several
months. It looked like there was going
to be a breakthrough in relations. Yeah,
so the the
why do we need to militarily intervene
down there?
It's not because we can't. Can we
overpower Venezuela militarily?
Obviously.
>> Mhm. That's not that challenging.
That's not to say that after you've done
this so that you're sitting on a gold
mine. On the contrary, the big problem
is you go into a place like that,
there's the risk that you make yourself
responsible for everything that happens
down there. You ultimately turn it into
a bottomless pit for money and resources
from the United States at a point in
time when I don't think we could afford
that or or necessarily need to do it.
Uh and then what kind of response do you
get out of Latin America?
Uh we're not widely loved in what Latin
America, never have been.
Some of that is justified, some of it
isn't, it doesn't matter.
But if you go into Venezuela, do you
turn this whole episode into a rallying
point for every Latin American country,
every contented revolutionary, uh
100,000 paramilitaries from, say, Brazil
and potentially Colombia that also pile
in there to fight you at some point?
And then you've got this population of
almost 30 million inside a state that's
uh
about the size of Germany, France, and
Switzerland combined.
Now, I know they have emerald mines, I
know they have gold mines, but again,
are we adopting a sort of Viking-like uh
policy that says, "You've got what we
want. We're landing on your shores and
we're taking everything."
Uh I don't necessarily think that's what
we as Americans want to be as 21st
century Vikings.
Maybe that's part of the plan.
I haven't figured it out. Now, the other
connection, as you know, is China. And
of course, there is uh
Russia.
Well, the Chinese were very frustrated
down there with Hugo Chavez. He wasn't
paying the interest on his debt. The
Chinese have mixed feelings about
getting deeply involved there.
And Russia, of course,
did a did business with Maduro, provided
he paid for everything in gold.
And in fact, I have friends that were
down there and watched the the loaded
onto aircraft that were then flown to
Russia.
Okay. Wow. What's that got to do with
Venezuela at this point? Well, you know,
they're an outpost of evil in the
Western Hemisphere. We've got to drive
them out. I I guess.
Um
I I don't know. I mean, I listened to
someone who told me who's
has the background similar to your own.
Doug, we're flipping the board. Flipping
the board on Russia and China. This it's
good times are rolling again. We're back
in the game.
Really?
That actually That actually
leads me to another question.
Something that you and I briefly
discussed offline.
Donald Trump
in the very in the first term, it
appeared that Donald Trump was changing
the face of the Republican Party. It
looked like the Republican Party was
walking away from being the party of
neo-conservatism. And in fact, it was
the Democrats that became the
neoliberals, the warmongers, the ones
who were the biggest
supporters of the CIA and of covert
action overseas.
Now, in the second term,
it seems that that wasn't necessarily
the case, especially in the Senate.
There are a lot of Republicans who all
of a sudden are willing to stand up and
say, "No, they like the old days
better."
What I'm getting at is
there are fewer [snorts] Americans
today,
percentage-wise,
who call themselves Democrats or
Republicans
than we've seen in a century.
And a lot of people, including yourself,
people who are, you know, fixtures in
Washington,
are saying that it's time for another
political party or two.
So,
do you think that's where we are? I
mean, they you know, the conventional
wisdom is, "Look, we've got other
political parties. We've got a
Libertarian Party. We've got a Green
Party. There's the Reform Party and the
I forget what the other one is, the, you
know, America whatever party."
None of them amount to anything. You
know that the that the Libertarians are
going to get 1 and 1/2 percentage points
and the and the Greens are going to get
a little bit less than 1%. Those are not
viable parties.
But there's a lot of talk about the need
for a viable party.
Start off giving us your thoughts on
this. Well, you know, we just held a
meeting in Dallas on this very issue. It
was a a very small meeting. There were
only 50 guests.
And the whole point was to discuss
exactly this.
You know, most of us now feel like we're
the party of the outs as opposed to the
ins.
The ins consist of Democrats and
Republicans.
And ultimately, behind doors, they
hammer out policy and decide issues that
really serve the interests of the
members
who profit enormously from donors for
whatever policy decisions they make.
They no longer represent two clearly
different approaches to government.
Their approaches are very very similar.
Now, there are people in both parties on
the outskirts or the what do you want to
call it, the extreme ends one way or the
other who are a little different, but
they don't amount to much. The
overwhelming majority of people that
hold office today,
they're not really represent the
interests of you or me.
And that's what people came to Dallas to
talk about. We call it the
nationalconversation.org.
That's the organization.
A lot of good people have shown up and
said, "We want to participate." We
decided to keep the first meeting small.
We want to hold other meetings around
the country. We don't have all the
answers.
But what we are looking for, I guess,
is a is a set of principles or policies
that we think most Americans on any any
given day can support, whether they're
Democrats or Republicans.
And I think those things to would be
very simplistic. We want prosperity at
home. We want the rule of law.
And we want an end to the overseas
interventions. These pointless wars
that, frankly, we don't think we need to
fight.
Now, you and I know that there are a lot
of people in Washington
who have profited enormously
from the conflicts.
>> enormously
All you have to do is just drive around
Great Falls, McLean, go over to Potomac,
Maryland. You can see all the
magnificent homes that all of these
people live in.
>> Yeah, and they're not all doctors.
No.
>> [laughter]
>> Not all doctors. But they're not even
all lawyers, either.
>> That's right. You're absolutely right.
And then you look at the senior military
leaders.
And we've been through a change that's
been going on for decades. When
Eisenhower left office, he talked about
the military-industrial-congressional
complex.
He dropped out congressional because one
of the speechwriters said, "Mr.
President,
do you really want to say congressional?
Aren't we going to make enough enemies
with just military-industrial?"
But it was originally
military-industrial-congressional.
And he was very concerned about the
senior ranks of the armed forces
because he saw something that he had
never witnessed in his lifetime.
And that is that people went into the
military to achieve high rank for the
purpose of retiring and making lots of
money.
Now, what is what's wrong with that?
There's no reason why if someone leaves
the military, they can't make money.
Yeah, but there's a problem when to do
so,
you identify early on with a set of
policies or political interests or
people in politics
that promise to pay you well
if you do what they like.
You know, we've lost a sense that we
once had
back during the Korean War
when I said just before I said I took
over.
And there were meetings and senior
officers said, "Look,
this Korean War is the wrong war in the
wrong place against the wrong people."
That's what the That's what the general
said. Well, well, they were right.
And so the politicians said, "Okay,
well, then what do we do?"
Well, that's a better situation to be in
if you can get agreement that this is
the wrong war in the wrong place for the
wrong reason.
And we don't care what the reason is and
we don't care where it is. We don't even
care how long it lasts. Let's all go.
Why? Well, everybody's being rewarded
financially after they leave the service
for doing so. And everybody who's a
four-star or three-star knows, "Hey, you
get on board with this, when you get
out, you're going to be taken care of."
So, it's a huge problem. We're bribing
people
before they ever leave the service.
And people are not coming into the
service for the right reasons because
you can only do that for so long before
the lieutenants, captains, majors,
lieutenant colonels say, "Well,
gosh, look how General so-and-so, how
well he's doing. You know, he got on
board and he's got millions of dollars.
And what do you have, McGregor?
You don't have millions of dollars.
Well, what's wrong with you?"
Well, you're not on the right side of
the issue. I mean, I don't know how many
times I've talked to my West Point
classmates who said, "Doug,
what's happened to you?
You don't understand."
Well, they're right. I don't understand
it. I can't sign up for something I
think is patently wrong.
Yeah, yeah. Stick with the program.
forces. You know, what about these dumb
policies
that want to put women in tanks and
women in the infantry formations and put
them on the battlefield. Has everybody
lost their mind? Do they not understand
what happens in war?
War is not
civilization. It's not peacetime. In
other words,
war is the absence of moral restraint.
And when you got hundreds of thousands
or tens of thousands of men
who reckon with a high possibility that
they could lose their lives,
the last thing they need are lots of
nice young women in their midst before
they go into action.
Bad things happen. We know that from
5,000 years of military history. If this
was such a good idea, hey, why didn't
the Romans do it?
You know, why didn't the Spartans take
their women to war? Come on, wake up.
Smell the coffee. Don't be stupid.
But this has been going on. And if you
want to be a general, you want to be an
admiral, well, here's a whole I think
we're we're more enlightened now.
Yeah, right. We've all become
Renaissance men. We're all legal
scholars.
>> Russians and Chinese laugh at us. Like
some of our some of our recruiting
commercials, the videos that have been
released by the military and by the CIA,
for example. They laugh at us. There was
a CIA recruiting video that came out, I
don't know, two years, three years ago,
where they're interviewing this woman
and she said, "I'm an autistic,
depressed, anxious lesbian, you know,
blah blah blah. And I have a home at the
CIA." And I was like, "Oh my god, that's
not the CIA I joined."
Well, the thing with the military right
now is that that's one aspect that's
just bad and allegedly President Trump
and Hegseth want to change that.
Great.
Get to it. I hope it works. They're
going to fight They're going to fight
some enemies on the hill over it. We'll
see about that.
But there's another issue. And the other
issue is, "Let's go to Timbuktu." Why?
Well, Timbuktu has been
involved in the drug trade. Timbuktu has
a Communist Party. Timbuktu, you know,
whatever is a danger to his neighbors.
It also sits on top of the best gold
mines in the region. So,
>> Exactly.
we're going to go there. And by the way,
we're we're going to deliver a better
life for everybody in Timbuktu and
they're going to be happy to see us. We
know that. I mean, how many times do you
have to go through this nonsense? And
then the regime change bit.
>> Oh. I always tell everybody this this
idea of regime change, that has its
roots with the Bolsheviks.
Trotsky was the the big advocate for
regime change. And he convinced all the
Bolsheviks that they should invade
Poland.
Said, "We'll crush the Poles and we'll
march to Germany and the German workers
will welcome us.
The German working class is with us in
this revolution."
Of course, at the time there was a man
named Stalin who sort of sat on the
sidelines and said, "These people are
all crazy. They don't know anything
about the Poles. They don't know
anything about the Germans." Well, the
rest is history. They marched into
Poland.
The Poles practically annihilated the
so-called Red Army and the Germans all
sat on the sidelines and watched and
said, "That's a good thing." And they
shot their communists. So, so the point
is, these are dumb ideas and they keep
recycling and recycling and recycling
and recycling.
You don't You don't get very far when
your  revolution, whether it's uh
an American one or a Bolshevik one,
doesn't matter, arrives on bayonets.
Its staying power is minimal. It's not
going to
So, why are we doing this?
I think it's a disaster. And for us in
particular in the Western Hemisphere,
I think we should be interested in
finding ways to secure our borders,
enforce the law. You know, that's a
that's an you know, a novel idea. People
are complaining about ICE. I say, "Well,
ICE is enforcing federal law."
Well, I don't like it. Well, Change the
law.
Yeah, you can change the law or you can
have the argument we did in 1861.
That argument turned out to say,
"Federal law is federal law and you will
obey it." So, that seems to have worked
pretty well for us for at least the last
249 years.
So, I think we should enforce federal
law.
But, you don't need to invade somebody
else's country to deal with this. The
other thing is we need to be much
tougher on the drug peddlers here in the
United States.
The people that engage in human
trafficking. We lose 300,000 children a
year in this country. You don't know
where they went. That's outrageous.
I mean, people should be afraid to touch
a child for fear they're going to be
arrested, prosecuted, and executed. And
people say, "Well, I don't agree with
that." Well, what's your solution?
Invade Venezuela? Right.
>> You want to invade Mexico? I don't want
to invade Mexico. I just want to secure
the border.
And I want to crush anybody inside the
United States involved in this drug
trade or human trafficking.
And you know, it just it it just doesn't
ring
It doesn't ring any bells that instead
you have the other problem and you know
this, John.
We have inside the United States what I
call the bombs away club.
They're They're the people that as soon
as you drop bombs on anybody anywhere,
they say, "Oh, it's great. Yeah, we're
tough. We're the best.
This demonstrates that America is back."
You know,
Have you ever seen that silly thing that
used to
What is it? Uh
Uh Americans USA. It was a It was a
puppet thing where they were running
around and say, "Yeah, USA USA America
screw you."
>> [laughter]
>> It was ridiculous. It was absurd, but
unfortunately, we got a lot of people
that think that way.
>> Yeah, we do. And they'll show up and
cheer anybody. It doesn't matter if it's
Donald Trump or or Joe Biden. If you're
bombing somebody somewhere, they'll say,
"Hey, good good job. That's great."
Those people shouldn't be in charge.
Doug, in in 2016,
I traveled around the Western United
States with Governor Gary Johnson, the
former Republican governor of New
Mexico. He was the Libertarian Party's
nominee for president. And so, I
introduced him at campaign stops in in
12 Western states.
And one of the things that he confided
in me was that the reason why the
Libertarian Party would never really
amount to anything nationally,
electorally,
was that it didn't have a rabbi,
financial rabbi. There was There was a a
man that he referred to as the canned
tomato king of California who had
donated a couple of hundred thousand
dollars. We We bought a a motor home and
we drove from state to state.
But, there was no Sheldon Adelson giving
money to the Libertarian Party. And so,
there was no advertising.
Um
How can
a startup group overcome
the the bias against it
that comes as a result of a lack of
access to funding?
No, you're 100% right. Uh
we talked about that. In fact, we talked
about the origins of the Republican
Party.
The Republican Party in the 1850s really
wasn't much of a force.
>> No, it was a startup.
Yes, and uh something changed.
>> Mhm.
Something was
abolitionism.
In other words,
they became the
party that advocated the abolition of
slavery.
When that happened,
everything changed.
Money poured in, support came in, but
there was something even more important.
And that's what we call the John Brown
moment.
You'll recall John Brown came across
Harper's Ferry, which is not very far
from where I am. Uh
And he tried to raise slaves in revolt.
He wanted to liberate the slaves. It all
came to a pretty quick close. There were
very few people injured. One or two
people were killed, including one of his
sons.
But, what really made a difference was
that the
the very foolish governor of Virginia at
the time uh he said,
"What do you think I should do?" to his
advisers.
And most of his advisers privately said,
"Let the Let this man go.
I mean, he was very eloquent in court.
He's a very religious man.
He believes that what he was doing is
right. Most people agree that slavery
needs to go away. They just don't agree
on when and how.
But, there's no reason to harm this
man."
Somebody came to him and said, "You
know, governor,
if you execute John Brown, you're a
shoo-in for the Democratic nomination
for president at next year's
convention."
He said, "That's right." And so, he
executed John Brown.
What a catastrophe. And when that
happened, the Republican Party began
soaring because they had steadfastly
supported John Brown. They were opposed
to slavery and they said, "This is an
atrocity."
The rest is history and you get this
man, Lincoln,
who contrary to what a lot of people
think came out of nowhere. So, there are
two things involved. Yes, you're right.
We need money. We need people that are
willing to back us and help us build
this structure.
And then secondly, we need an exogenous
event,
an event over which we have no control,
that can make all the difference.
And I think that's coming. I think if
you look at the financial system right
now, it's very very brittle.
You know, that alone could put an end to
much of the overseas military
adventurism.
Uh although people will fight that.
They'd much rather have half the
population starve to death at home
before they start stop bombing someone
overseas.
But, I think it would happen.
Uh so, we can't predict the future, but
I see the appetite. Everywhere I go,
everybody I talk to says, "Ah, what a
disaster. Doesn't matter who you vote
for, you always get John McCain.
Doesn't matter what you try to do, no
one will change or reform health care.
Doesn't matter what you do." I mean,
just go down the list of all the issues
that are important to Americans, health
care,
inflation, and so forth. Who Who's doing
anything? And the answer is nobody does.
The guy who is a genius at this sort of
thing, at convincing everybody that
something's happening when it isn't, is
of course
Donald Trump.
But, Donald Trump's also on some fragile
ground right now
because he's promised a lot of things.
He's said a lot of things. And we can go
all the way back to before he was
elected. "I can end this war in Ukraine
in in 24 hours. I can end it on a phone
call."
Uh-huh.
Yeah, but this is somebody who doesn't
study anything. He doesn't doesn't
really listen well to briefings. He gets
He becomes bored. He likes to be the
smartest man in the room. And if you can
convince him he's the smartest man in
the room and whatever idea you came up
with is really his, he's going to do it.
He likes that.
So, I don't know how much longer this
goes on because I I sense that people
are beginning to say, you know, I didn't
vote for this. This is not what I
wanted.
Can't we get back to the original
agenda, which as you and I discussed at
the beginning, is America focused?
Now, he has something though that that
we don't.
He has a single issue lobby behind him.
And that lobby represents enormous
Jewish financial power here inside the
United States and around the world.
And they will do anything to commit all
the military power and resources of the
United States to whatever Mr. Netanyahu
wants.
That's a big advantage. But, even that
might not turn out to work too much
longer.
Well, that's a very important point,
actually. Um
The The Times of Israel
said just a couple of days ago
that this recent trip
the two trips to Israel by Vice
President Vance and Secretary of State
Rubio were specifically to to BB-sit,
uh which is what they they called it. Uh
Donald Trump has been publicly angry at
Bibi Netanyahu over the past week or two
and has even taken to to threatening
him. I think that's exactly what we
should be doing. We should be
threatening Benjamin Netanyahu. But, do
you think anything will come of that
over the long term? I think we have My
own personal
personal belief is that we have bent
over backwards to support the Israelis
to the point where it is actually hurt
American national interests. So have we
seen enough of this pandering to the
Israelis or should we expect more? And
and this is not specific to Donald
Trump. The Democrats are at least as
guilty as the Republicans are.
I think two things. First of all, and I
said this yesterday, I think I was
talking to Judge Napolitano and then
later in the evening to Matt Gates.
I I don't listen too much to what people
say in Washington. I try to watch
carefully what they actually do.
Uh we've heard these kinds of statements
before. Let's be frank, anybody who
spent any time with Bibi Netanyahu
doesn't walk away in love with Bibi
Netanyahu.
Uh it doesn't matter.
What matters is what do they actually
do?
You and I look I I don't know what your
track record is. I freely admit that I
have supported the Israelis for years.
Oh, I did. I did for years. Okay. Well,
I'm a big I was always an advocate for
helping them defend themselves.
But within 2 weeks of the Gaza
business, it became pretty obvious to me
that this didn't have anything to do
with defending Israel. Totally agree.
>> I had been down at the headquarters that
Israeli Defense Force headquarters that
is responsible for the Southern Command.
And I can tell you that they had a grip
on Gaza that was absolutely beyond
anything I've ever seen anywhere else in
the world. They if someone picked up a
cell phone
out of, you know, millions of people and
said something, they knew about it. If
if there was someone that took a shot at
someone across the
you know, zone,
tried to shoot an Israeli soldier in a
tower, bang, they knew who that was
instantly.
So when this happened, I was very
suspicious because it just didn't track
with my experience. Shin Bet, the
Mossad, and the the professional
leadership of the Israeli Defense Force
too competent.
Where where was the reaction force? Uh
where was the instantaneous alarm, you
know, that should have risen? Then we
find out about the Israeli women who
were part of an intelligence cell who
say they reported this over and over and
over again well in advance saying this
something's coming, this is what we've
seen. Then you have the Deputy Chief of
Staff for Intelligence in Egypt. And of
course, the Egyptians have always been
very wary of Hamas.
And they said, "We see a giant attack
coming from Hamas. What are you doing to
get ready for this?"
So I I finally walked away and said,
"This is a This was designed to trigger
this larger campaign
against everybody in the region that
Israel wants to destroy." And they saw
this as an ideal opportunity to drag us
in.
And we have willingly walked in.
I don't see that ending anytime soon.
I think it's going to continue
until we are hurt in some way. And I
know that sounds awful,
but until we are actually hurt,
uh there's not going to be any support.
I mean, Churchill had this problem in
1940.
Uh I remember when they bombed the
shipyards uh in Glasgow, the docks.
And Churchill came in and said, "Thank
God."
He said, "Otherwise, we'd never have any
of the Scots on our side in this war
because the Scots, they lost a lot of
people in the First World War and they
came back and said, 'What did we do this
for?'"
"When were the Germans the enemy?"
I mean, English were different in their
attitudes, but in Scotland and Ireland,
that's a very different attitude.
So when they bombed the place, Churchill
said, "This is wonderful." Well, I I
kind of get the impression that
that hasn't really happened for Trump
and and the Israel lobby. The opposite
could happen though. If you do get a lot
of Americans killed somewhere, they'll
try to spin it, but it's going to make a
lot of people here angry. And what
[snorts] do you think this means for the
Saudis? You know,
the backdrop to all of this is the
Abraham Accords. The Abraham Accords,
the Abraham Accords, every single time
somebody mentions whatever peace deal,
it has to include the Saudis. The Saudis
don't seem to be in any rush to
recognize Israel. And when push comes to
shove, what do the Saudi Saudis really
get out of a relationship with Israel?
I'm unable to identify anything. And I
spent most of my adult life in the
Middle East. What do you think about
this? I suspect that their interests are
purely financial. Yeah. And they won't
do anything that could disrupt the flow
of cash into or out of Saudi Arabia.
They've already begun to take
precautions in in other kinds of ways.
You know, the Chinese have now opened a
gold vault
in Riyadh. They've got another one in
Hong Kong. Now, this is separate from
the Shanghai Gold Exchange.
This is designed to facilitate
transactions across international lines.
So as a result of this, the Saudis are
now bought are now selling oil in yuan.
And they're buying things from China in
yuan.
We're going to see a lot more of this in
the future with BRICS. This is just the
beginning.
>> Ah, yeah. You've anticipated my next
question, too. But go ahead and finish
your thought. No, it's just that I think
the Saudis are very good at playing both
sides to the middle.
They don't want to invite trouble from
us and Israel, but at the same time
they're prepared to jump ship quickly as
needed. And they're going to enjoy a
certain amount of support from the
Chinese and probably also the Russians
and others as a result of doing so. Iran
has already jumped ship, we know that.
And the Israelis, you know, are are
interested because we're interested in
disrupting all of this. You know, the
Israeli goal is very simple. Let's
balkanize the region.
If they can balkanize Syria, if they can
balkanize Iran, if they can balkanize
the Arabian Peninsula, if they can
balkanize Egypt, they'll do it. Because
in their judgment, when all of these
peoples are fragmented and divided and
ideally killing each other,
then Israel wins and Israel is safe.
I'm not sure it's going to quite work
out that way in the next few years, but
that's certainly the goal.
So if you look at Saudi Arabia right
now, I would say
they're going to migrate in direction of
what profits them. Now, there's always
the outside possibility that no one is
considering, and that is that the
peninsular Arabs decide to overthrow
their
ruling elites.
That's not impossible.
Because the ruling elites right now are
really unpopular.
>> Yes. I'm surprised Sisi is still where
he is in Egypt.
>> Mhm. Because my perception of the our
Egyptian friends is they are furious
beyond belief. You have a similar
phenomenon, by the way, with Erdogan.
Erdogan talks tough,
but when it comes to acting, he does
nothing.
And the people in Turkey, they they're
well aware of the fragility of the
Turkish economy. They understand it.
They understand it.
>> it every day.
Mhm.
>> But
they would all sign up to go to war
against Israel.
Yeah, I think that's exactly right. I
mean, the level of hostility and
animosity in that region today is
something I have never seen before.
Yeah, I have to agree. I want to ask you
question about international finance and
then I'm going to move to Iran. Um a
year ago,
the Kuwaitis sold
a shipment of oil to the Chinese and for
the first time ever, the Chinese paid
for that shipment in yuan, not in
dollars.
Uh there's talk that the Saudis are now
dealing with the Chinese in yuan rather
than in dollars.
It seems to me that that's the first
step
toward the end of the American empire.
There's also talk of the BRICS countries
creating eventually uh a unified
currency like the euro.
That would be the death knell for the
dollar.
Do you think that's where we're heading
or is there a way for the United States
to to maintain its
its top position in in international
finance?
Um two things. First, invading Venezuela
and waging war in the Middle East on
behalf of Israel will not stop that
process, it will accelerate it.
>> Indeed. So that's the first part. Second
part is that
uh
they're a long way from a unified
currency as you put it.
Uh their banking system is clearly not
as sophisticated as ours, but they're
developing rapidly. Uh people are really
shocked that they've already got the
equivalent of Swift uh operating. And by
the way, it's much I'm told it's much
better and more effective and more
efficient than Swift.
>> Everything goes through Shanghai instead
of New York, so it's not liable to uh to
sanctions.
The other thing is, remember that before
World War broke out, I would say
certainly before the Japanese invasion
in 1937,
Shanghai was the financial center of
Asia.
People are always telling me, "Aren't
you worried about the Chinese?" And I
said, "Well, for about the last 2,000
years, with the exception of the last
couple of hundred, China was always the
richest country in the world."
But the reason that peoples associate
wealth and power with the projection of
military power is because that's what we
do.
But that's not necessarily the Chinese
inclination.
Now, the worst thing that we could do is
try to start a war with the Chinese. And
I I I've heard less of it recently,
thank goodness, but there's still a lot
of foolish people out there that think
this is somehow or another an inevitable
event and a good idea.
But to answer your question, I I we're
on that road. It's not going to happen
overnight. It's going to take time.
The The real question is not whether
whether we can preserve our position as
the reserve currency. I think we could.
Because I can tell you from my
conversations with Chinese
officials and so forth, they they don't
want to be the reserve currency. They're
perfectly willing to have us do that.
Uh
China's interests are not the same as
Western interests. You know, this is a
big problem. We're always treating the
Japanese, the Chinese, the Koreans, the
Vietnamese, the Malays, anybody as
though well, they're just like us. No,
they're not. They don't think like us.
They're not inclined to do the things
that we do. Very different group of
people.
Left [clears throat] alone, the Asians
will fall over each other to avoid a
war.
There will be no war in that region
unless we start it.
We You know, people don't get it. So, I
think we need to take that for granted.
The question is what do we do? And
you've already pointed to the lots of
the stupid things that we're engaged in
right now
that'll put ourselves at risk
unnecessarily financially
and drive people away from us making our
currency irrelevant. What I think
long-term is that
you'll probably have the United States
and Europe, and I'm talking about North
America and Europe probably.
Maybe others. I don't know if the
Australians will be in that or not.
That'll be one financial system.
And then there's the rest of the world.
Now, it it would be nice if there were a
way to do business with Latin America,
but I you know,
doesn't look good right now.
I want to ask you about Iran.
Uh
the Iranians it's been a momentous year
for Iran, not in not necessarily in a
good way. Uh they've been bombed
repeatedly by Israel. They they
practice something that people are
calling strategic patience.
Uh the Israelis bomb them.
Then they send some slow drones across.
It takes 6 hours to get to Israel. Most
of them are are shot down.
Uh
they uh they're bombed again. And then
they launch something at uh at
at the Israelis again that
does nothing but saves face.
And then the Israelis bomb them and the
US bombs them.
They finally responded by by firing at
uh
at
uh cutter.
Just one rocket.
Nobody was injured. No big deal.
How long can this go on? And do you
think that this policy of strategic
patience
is going to matter in the face of what
appears to be an Israeli decision to
take this government down?
Well, this is an important question. I I
think the Iranian government has tried
very hard
to put the past behind them with regard
to us and their own revolution, I would
argue.
It's been 40 years since this
revolution. If anybody thinks that
nothing has changed in 40 years, they're
crazy.
Uh Iran is a very different society
today. The Iranians are very different
from what they were 40 years ago.
Uh if you listen to the Israelis,
nothing's changed. Khomeini uh you know,
was recently resuscitated and is walking
the streets of Tehran.
Uh that's not true. Things have changed
quite a bit.
The other thing the Israelis I think
have begun to understand is that their
actions have actually forced cohesion on
the country.
Yes.
>> They were hoping to fragment it, to
divide it, to balkanize it.
Uh they had cultivated and they still
have a base of support in Azerbaijan
from which they would like to launch
major attacks into Iran.
Uh that may yet work. I don't know, but
I don't think they're going to be able
to invade northern Iran and raise the
Azeri Turks who are Shiites in in
rebellion against Iran. I don't see that
happening. Agreed.
Uh they've always besides always been
down off and on in years in Baluchistan
trying to get the Baluchis to do
something.
I mean, here Iran is a diverse place.
But their overarching Persian identity
and culture and language, I think that's
stronger than anybody thought and now
it's perhaps stronger than it's been in
many many decades.
The other thing is it was a tendency to
dismiss the Iranians as they were simply
like other
small Arab states in the region. They
may be bigger in population, bigger in
size, but there's no real difference.
That of course is a serious
>> Not true.
And you know, I said this 3 years ago. I
wrote it in my last book, Margin of
Victory, when I talked about I have a
whole chapter on the Israelis
in their fight with the Egyptians in '73
and I made the point at the end of that.
Don't take anything for it granted that
in the sense that don't expect the
future will look like the past.
Tremendous tremendous strides have been
achieved in terms of literacy and
education and understanding. You've got
a lot of really smart people now in the
Middle East. Very bright people.
The Iranians have great high human
capital.
Why we continue to believe otherwise is
a mystery to me.
And they should be concerned about
Iran's capacity to do real damage. Now,
I think they had a taste of that during
the 12-day war. But even then the
Iranians exercised restraint.
So, the real question is if they are put
under the gun again by Israel, will they
exercise restraint?
I think it'll be much less restraint. My
great fear is that once once it begins,
the Israelis will be tempted to use a
nuclear weapon.
And of course, they they would probably
launch those from their Dolphin-class
submarines which the Germans
gave them and then altered the tubes so
that they could accommodate a nuclear
warhead on
a long-range missiles.
But I think the the real the real
question is will they say, "If you don't
come in and rescue us, we will use a
nuclear weapon."
And of course, at that point I think we
would do almost anything
to avoid the use of a nuclear weapon.
But what does that do to us?
And that's that's the real question.
Again, it's back to
do Americans suffer? You see, most
Americans and you again, I'm not telling
you anything you don't know.
Most Americans on any given day don't
give a damn what happens beyond the
borders of the United States.
Go to Kansas City. Go to St. Louis. Go
out to Coeur d'Alene in Idaho.
Everybody's got a life out there.
Doesn't really matter much to them what
happens on the other side of the planet.
But it will in the future. And if
they're harmed,
seriously harmed financially,
economically, and God forbid physically,
then then the game is up completely for
the boys in Washington. What they think
in DC, if you talk to them, "Well, we'll
mobilize the country for war."
Huh?
I don't think so. This is not 1941.
You know, my my grandfather who's turned
out to be right about everything he ever
said,
used to tell me when I was growing up,
he said, "Well, that was FDR's war. You
know, he brought it on. He embargoed the
Japanese. Everybody knew that once you
did that, there was going to be a war."
Well, he was right. I didn't find out
till years later when I read all the
papers that Marshall, as soon as the
embargo was was announced, actually
beforehand, he knew it was coming in 30
days, he called the CNO
and said, "We have to have a meeting
immediately and plan for the war in the
Pacific.
The Japanese will be at war with Japan."
Of course, they were they made a bad
decision. They thought it would all
begin in the Philippines.
It never occurred to them that it would
involve the Philippines as well as
Hawaii and then ultimately the rest of
Asia. They Again, there was a failure to
appreciate the Japanese and their
capabilities.
So,
I guess I guess the kind of thing I
worry about at this stage is that
Americans are saying, "Well, you it's
not our problem. It's not coming here.
Don't worry about it."
And that's a bad position to take. They
ought to be interested in telling their
government, "Wait a minute. Why are we
doing this? We went through this in
Vietnam. Everybody was let's go kill
communists." You remember kill a commie
for Christ and all this kind of
business.
And by 1970 '71, it was what are we
doing here? What's the purpose? What's
the mission?
The best the best one anecdote of all,
and I'm sorry that this can't happen now
with somebody like Donald Trump, but he
probably wouldn't listen anyway.
LBJ in 1968
sent
Omar Bradley to Vietnam. He said, "Go
over there and tell me what you think.
Take as much time as you need then come
back and see me." So, he did.
And after I guess 45 days or so,
something like that, he came back and he
said, "Well, Mr. President,
I've been all over the country. I've
talked to everybody from privates to
four stars.
And nobody nobody I spoke to understands
what they're doing. They don't know what
they're there for. They don't even know
what the mission is."
And LBJ said, "Well, that's outrageous.
I can't believe that." So, he picked up
a
uh what do you call it? A legal pad. And
the pen said, "Mr. President, write down
the mission. What's the purpose?"
And LBJ took the pen and he started to
write and he said, "Well, you know, this
is this is going to take some time. I've
got to think
He said, "Then get out."
And that's what should happen today with
Donald Trump.
And that's what a four star should go in
and say to Mr. President, "Make it
abundantly clear to everyone what is the
military objective." Because it's always
political.
You know, we we say military, but it's
really political military.
What is the explicit mission? What are
we supposed to do?
Bombing people is not a mission. That's
an action.
And that's what that's what should go
on, but I don't see much evidence that
that's likely to happen, do you? No, I
don't at all.
No, I think this gets worse before it
gets any better.
I hate to say it.
>> on that happy note.
>> Yeah, [laughter] on that happy note.
Well, tell tell our viewers where they
can read more about your work and about
this conversation about a a new
political
political Well, I've got a website, you
know, that you can go to. It'll come up
if you go after my name despite Google's
attempts to suppress it. Indeed.
>> And
then but we have this new organization
called the nationalconversation.org.
And it has to be the
nationalconversation.org.
And if you go to that site, you'll see
what we're trying to do. You'll see some
film footage from the discussions that
we had on 4 October. It's just
highlights. And there's some statements
on there from me and from others about
what we're trying to achieve, which is
what we discussed about looking for a
third way forward. And we think that
contrary to popular belief, this is a
good time to start. We think that things
will change in the future. The future
will not look like the past. But as you
point out, we need support. We need
people that [music] want to support some
alternative. The people that don't want
John McCain in the White House anymore.
>> Mhm.
Regardless of whether it's John McCain
the Republican or John McCain the
Democrat. That's the same thing over and
over and over again, right? Over
>> It is.
Colonel Doug McGregor, thank you so much
for joining us. Ladies and gentlemen, if
you enjoyed this podcast and you like
the content that we normally provide,
please do me that favor of subscribing
as well as liking and sharing it with
your friends. Doug, thanks again. It's
great to see you.